<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Configuration Builder Howto</title>
  <author email="oheger@apache.org">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
	<section name="Using DefaultConfigurationBuilder">
    <p>
      The <code>ConfigurationFactory</code> class that was introduced in the
      <a href="howto_configurationfactory.html#Using_a_Configuration_Factory">last
      section</a> is a powerful tool for dealing with multiple different
      configuration sources, but it also has some shortcomings:
      <ul>
        <li>The format for configuration definition files is not extensible.</li>
        <li>Complex initializations of the declared configuration sources (e.g.
        for assigning a reloading strategy) are not supported.</li>
        <li>The returned configuration object is not hierarchical, which limits
        the query facilities somewhat.</li>
        <li>Declared configuration sources can only be accessed by index from the
        returned composite configuration, which means that code using a
        <code>ConfigurationFactory</code> depends on the order of declarations
        in a configuration definition file.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      To work around these limitations the class
      <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/DefaultConfigurationBuilder.html">
      DefaultConfigurationBuilder</a></code> was introduced.
    </p>

    <subsection name="ConfigurationFactory Differences">
	<p>
      From its basic usage scenarios <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> is
      very similar to <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>. It is able to process
      the same configuration definition files as can be read by
      <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>, but supports more options. The following
      list identifies the main differences between these classes:
	</p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li><code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> extends <code>XMLConfiguration</code>.
        This means that it is a <a href="howto_filebased.html#File-based Configurations">
        file-based configuration</a>, and thus supports multiple ways of
        specifying the location of the configuration definition file (e.g.
        as <code>java.io.File</code> object, as URL, etc.).</li>
        <li>The configuration object returned by a <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
        is an instance of the <a href="howto_combinedconfiguration.html#Combined Configuration">
        CombinedConfiguration</a> class, i.e. a truely hierarchical
        configuration supporting enhanced query facilities.</li>
        <li>Each declaration of a configuration source in the configuration
        definition file is interpreted as a
        <a href="howto_beans.html#Declaring and Creating Beans">bean
        declaration</a>, so complex initializations are supported.</li>
        <li><code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> supports custom tags in its
        configuration definition file. For this purpose a so-called
        <em>configuration provider</em> has to be registered, which will be
        called when a corresponding tag is encountered.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Enhancements to the configuration definition file">
    <p>
      As was already pointed out, <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
      maintains compatibility with <code>ConfigurationFactory</code> in that it
      understands the same configuration definition files. In addition to the
      elements that are allowed in a configuration definition file for
      <code>ConfigurationFactory</code> the data files for
      <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> support some additional options
      providing greater flexibility. This section explains these enhanced
      features.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Overall structure of a configuration definition file</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      A configuration definition file for <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
      can contain three sections, all of which are optional. A skeleton looks as
      follows:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>

<configuration systemProperties="path to property file">
  <header>
    <!-- Meta data about the resulting combined configuration -->
  </header>
  <override>
    <!-- Configuration declarations with override semantics -->
  </override>
  <additional>
    <!-- Configuration declarations that form a union configuration -->
  </additional>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      <strong>Declaring configuration sources</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>override</code> and <code>additional</code> sections should look
      familar to users that have already worked with
      <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>. They have the exact same purpose here,
      i.e. they contain declarations for the configuration sources to be
      embedded. For compatibility reasons it is also allowed to declare
      configuration sources outside these sections; they are then treated as if
      they were placed inside the <code>override</code> section.
    </p>
    <p>
      Each declaration of a configuration source is represented by an XML
      element whose name determines the type of the configuration source (e.g.
      <code>properties</code> for properties files, or <code>xml</code> for
      XML documents). Per default all configuration types are supported that
      are also allowed for <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>. A list of all
      supported tags can be found
      <a href="howto_configurationfactory.html#Configuration definition file reference">here</a>.
      In addition to the default tags provided by <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>
      <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> knows the following tags:
    </p>
    <p>
      <dl>
        <dt>configuration</dt>
        <dd>The <code>configuration</code> tag allows other configuration
        definition files to be included. This makes it possible to nest these
        definition files up to an arbitrary depth. In fact, this tag will
        create another <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> object,
        initialize it, and obtain the <code>CombinedConfiguation</code> from it.
        This combined configuration will then be added to the resulting
        combined configuration. Like all file-based configurations the
        <code>fileName</code> attribute can be used to specify the configuration
        definition file to be loaded. This file must be an XML document that
        conforms to the format described here. Some of the most important
        settings are copied from the original <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
        object to the newly created builder:
        <ul>
        <li>the base path under which configuration files are searched</li>
        <li>some flags, e.g. for controlling delimiter parsing or throwing
        exceptions on missing properties</li>
        <li>the logger</li>
        <li>the configuration and error listeners</li>
        </ul>
        </dd>
        <dt>ini</dt>
        <dd>This tag can be used to include an ini file into the resulting
        combined configuration. Behind the scenes an instance of
        <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration/INIConfiguration.html">
        INIConfiguration</a></code> is used to load the ini file.</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <p>
      In the declaration of a configuration source it is possible to set
      properties on the corresponding configuration objects. Configuration
      declarations are indeed
      <a href="howto_beans.html#Declaring and Creating Beans">Bean
      declarations</a>. That means they can have attributes matching simple
      properties of the configuration object to create and sub elements
      matching complex properties. The following example fragment shows how
      complex initialization can be performed in a configuration declaration:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
  <properties fileName="test.properties" throwExceptionOnMissing="true">
    <reloadingStrategy refreshDelay="10000"
    config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration.reloading.FileChangedReloadingStrategy"/>
  </properties>
  <xml fileName="test.xml" delimiterParsingDisabled="true">
    <expressionEngine config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration.tree.DefaultExpressionEngine"
      propertyDelimiter="/" indexStart="[" indexEnd="]"/>
  </xml>
]]></source>
    <p>
      In this example a configuration source for a properties file and one for
      an XML document are defined. For the properties source the
      <code>throwExceptionOnMissing</code> property is set to <b>true</b>,
      which means that it should throw an exception if a requested property is
      not found. In addition it is assigned a reloading strategy, which is
      declared and configured in a sub element. The XML configuration source is
      initialized in a similar way: a simple property is set, and an expression
      engine is assigned. More information about the format for declaring objects
      and initializing their properties can be found in the section about
      <a href="howto_beans.html#Declaring and Creating Beans">bean
      declarations</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      In addition to the attributes that correspond to properties of the
      configuration object to be created, a configuration declaration can have a
      set of special attributes that are evaluated by
      <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> when it creates the objects.
      These attributes are listed in the following table:
    </p>
    <p>
    <table border="1">
    <tr>
      <th>Attribute</th>
      <th>Meaning</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td valign="top"><code>config-name</code></td>
      <td>Allows a name to be specified for this configuration. This name can
      be used to obtain a reference to the configuration from the resulting
      combined configuration (see below).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td valign="top"><code>config-at</code></td>
      <td>With this attribute an optional prefix can be specified for the
      properties of the corresponding configuration.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td valign="top"><code>config-optional</code></td>
      <td>Declares a configuration as optional. This means that errors that
      occur when creating the configuration are silently ignored. The default
      behavior when an error occurs is that no configuration is added to
      the resulting combined configuration. This behavior can be used to find
      out whether an optional configuration could be successfully created or
      not. If you specify a name for the optional configuration (using the
      <code>config-name</code> attribute), you can later check whether the
      combined configuration contains a configuration with this name. With the
      <code>config-forceCreate</code> attribute (see below) this default
      behavior can be changed.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td valign="top"><code>config-forceCreate</code></td>
      <td>This boolean attribute is only evaluated for configurations declared as
      optional. It determines the behavior of the configuration builder when
      the optional configuration could not be created. If set to <b>true</b>,
      the builder tries to create an empty, uninitialized configuration of the
      correct type and add it to the resulting combined configuration. This is
      especially useful for file-based configurations. Consider a use case
      where an application wants to store user specific configuration files in
      the users' home directories. When a user starts this application for the
      first time, the user configuration does not exist yet. If it is declared
      as <em>optional</em> and <em>forceCreate</em>, the missing configuration
      file won't cause an error, but an empty configuration will be created.
      The application can then obtain this configuration, add properties to it
      (e.g. user specific settings) and save it. Without the
      <code>config-forceCreate</code> attribute the application would have to
      check whether the user configuration exists in the combined configuration
      and eventually create it manually. Note that not all configuration
      providers support this mechanism. Sometimes it may not be possible to
      create an empty configuration if the standard initialization fails. In
      this case no configuration will be added to the combined configuration
      (with other words: the <code>config-forceCreate</code> attribute will not
      have any effect).</td>
    </tr>
    </table>
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>config-at</code> and <code>config-optional</code> attributes
      have the same meaning as the <code>at</code> and <code>optional</code>
      attributes for <code>ConfigurationFactory</code>. For compatibility
      reasons the old attributes without the <code>config-</code> prefix are
      still supported. Note that the <code>config-at</code> is now allowed for
      override configurations, too (<code>ConfigurationFactory</code> evaluated
      the <code>at</code> attribute only for configuration declarations in the
      <code>additional</code> section).
    </p>
    <p>
      Another useful feature is the built-in support for interpolation (i.e.
      variable substitution): You can use variables in your configuration
      definition file that are defined in declared configuration sources. For
      instance, if the name of a configuration file to be loaded is defined by
      the system property <code>CONFIG_FILE</code>, you can do something like
      this:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <!-- Load the system properties -->
  <system/>
  <!-- Now load the config file, using a system property as file name -->
  <properties fileName="${CONFIG_FILE}"/>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      Note that you can refer only to properties that have already been loaded.
      If you change the order of the <code>&lt;system&gt;</code> and the
      <code>&lt;properties&gt;</code> elements in the example above, an error
      will occur because the <code>${CONFIG_FILE}</code> variable will then be
      undefined at the moment it is evaluated.
    </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
<configuration systemProperties="systemProperties.xml">
  <!-- Load the system properties -->
  <system/>
  <!-- Now load the config file, using a system property as file name -->
  <properties fileName="${CONFIG_FILE}"/>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      This example differs from the previous one by allowing CONFIG_FILE, and other
      properties, to be defined in a properties file and added to the system
      properties before the configuration is constructed.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>The header section</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      In the header section properties of the resulting combined configuration
      object can be set. The main part of this section is a bean declaration
      that is used for creating the resulting configuration object. Other
      elements can be used for customizing the
      <a href="howto_combinedconfiguration.html#Node combiners">Node combiners</a>
      used by the override and the union combined configuration. The following
      example shows a header section that uses all supported properties:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
  <header>
    <result delimiterParsingDisabled="true" forceReloadCheck="true">
      <nodeCombiner config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration2.tree.OverrideCombiner"/>
      <expressionEngine config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration2.tree.xpath.XPathExpressionEngine"/>
    </result>
    <combiner>
      <override>
        <list-nodes>
          <node>table</node>
          <node>list</node>
        </list-nodes>
      </override>
      <additional>
        <list-nodes>
          <node>table</node>
        </list-nodes>
      </additional>
    </combiner>
  </header>
]]></source>
    <p>
      The <code>result</code> element points to the bean declaration for the
      resulting combined configuration. In this example we set some attributes
      and initialize the node combiner (which is not necessary because the
      default override combiner is specified) and the expression engine to be
      used. Note that the <code>config-class</code> attribute makes it
      possible to inject custom classes for the resulting configuration or the
      node combiner.
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>combiner</code> section allows nodes to be defined as list nodes.
      This can be necessary for certain node combiner implementations to work
      correctly. More information can be found in the section about
      <a href="howto_combinedconfiguration.html#Node combiners">Node combiners</a>.
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="An example">
    <p>
      After all that theory let's go through an example! We start with the
      configuration definition file that looks like the following:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!-- Test configuration definition file that demonstrates complex initialization -->
<configuration>
  <header>
    <result delimiterParsingDisabled="true" forceReloadCheck="true">
      <expressionEngine config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration2.tree.xpath.XPathExpressionEngine"/>
    </result>
    <combiner>
      <additional>
        <list-nodes>
          <node>table</node>
        </list-nodes>
      </additional>
    </combiner>
  </header>
  <override>
    <properties fileName="user.properties" throwExceptionOnMissing="true"
      config-name="properties" config-optional="true">
      <reloadingStrategy refreshDelay="10000"
      config-class="org.apache.commons.configuration2.reloading.FileChangedReloadingStrategy"/>
    </properties>
    <xml fileName="settings.xml" config-name="xml"/>
  </override>
  <additional>
    <xml config-name="tab1" fileName="table1.xml" config-at="database.tables"/>
    <xml config-name="tab2" fileName="table2.xml" config-at="database.tables"
        validating="true"/>
  </additional>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      This configuration definition file includes four configuration sources and
      sets some properties for the resulting <code>CombinedConfiguration</code>.
      Of special interest is the <code>forceReloadCheck</code> property, which
      enables a special check for detecting property changes in the contained
      configuration sources. If this property is not set, reloading won't work.
      Because we have configured a reloading strategy for one of the included
      configuration sources we have to set this flag so that this reloading
      strategy can function properly. More details about this topic can be
      found in the Javadocs for
      <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/CombinedConfiguration.html">
      CombinedConfiguration</a></code>. We also set some properties for the
      configurations to be loaded; for instance we declare that one of the XML
      configurations should be validated.
    </p>
    <p>
      With the following code we can create a <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
      and load this file:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
DefaultConfigurationBuilder builder = new DefaultConfigurationBuilder();
builder.setFile(new File("configuration.xml"));
CombinedConfiguration cc = builder.getConfiguration(true);
]]></source>
    <p>
      It would have been possible to specify the location of the configuration
      definition file in multiple other ways, e.g. as a URL. The boolean argument
      in the call to <code>getConfiguration()</code> determines whether the
      configuration definition file should be loaded. For our simple example we
      want this to happen, but it would also be possible to load the file
      manually (by calling the <code>load()</code> method), and after that
      updating the configuration. (Remember that <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
      is derived from <code>XMLConfiguration</code>, that means you can use all methods
      provided by this class to alter its data, e.g. to add further configuration
      sources.) If the configuration's data was manually changed, you should
      call <code>getConfiguration()</code> with the argument <b>false</b>.
      <code>XMLConfiguration</code> also provides the <code>registerEntityId()</code>
      method that can be used to define the location of DTD files (refer to the
      section <a href="howto_xml.html#Validation_of_XML_configuration_files">
      Validation of XML configuration files</a> for more details). This method
      is available for <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>, too. The
      entities registered here will be passed to the loaded child XML
      configurations. So you can register the DTDs of all child XML configurations
      globally at the configuration builder.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the <code>header</code> section we have chosen an XPATH expression
      engine for the resulting configuration. So we can query our properties
      using the convenient XPATH syntax. By providing the <code>config-name</code>
      attribute we have given all configuration sources a name. This name can
      be used to obtain the corresponding sources from the combined
      configuration. For configurations in the override section this is
      directly possible:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
Configuration propertiesConfig = cc.getConfiguration("properties");
Configuration xmlConfig = cc.getConfiguration("xml");
]]></source>
    <p>
      Configurations in the <code>additional</code> section are treated a bit
      differently: they are all packed together in another combined configuration
      and then added to the resulting combined configuration. So in our example
      the combined configuration <code>cc</code> will contain three configurations:
      the two configurations from the override section, and the combined
      configuration with the <code>additional</code> configurations. The latter
      is stored under a name determined by the <code>ADDITIONAL_NAME</code>
      constant of <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>. The following
      code shows how the configurations of the <code>additional</code> section
      can be accessed:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
CombinedConfiguration ccAdd = (CombinedConfiguration)
  cc.getConfiguration(DefaultConfigurationBuilder.ADDITIONAL_NAME);
Configuration tab1Config = ccAdd.getConfiguration("tab1");
Configuration tab2Config = ccAdd.getConfiguration("tab2");
]]></source>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Extending the configuration definition file format">
    <p>
      If you have written a custom configuration class, you might want to
      declare instances of this class in a configuration definition file, too.
      With <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> this is now possible by
      registering a <em>ConfigurationProvider</em>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>ConfigurationProvider</code> is an inner class defined in
      <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>. Its task is to create and
      initialize a configuration object. Whenever <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code>
      encounters a tag in the <code>override</code> or the <code>additional</code>
      section it checks whether for this tag a <code>ConfigurationProvider</code>
      was registered. If this is the case, the provider is asked to create a
      new configuration instance; otherwise an exception will be thrown.
    </p>
    <p>
      So for adding support for a new configuration class you have to create an
      instance of <code>ConfigurationProvider</code> (or a derived class) and
      register it at the configuration builder using the
      <code>addConfigurationProvider()</code> method. This method expects the
      name of the associated tag and the provider instance as arguments.
    </p>
    <p>
      If your custom configuration class does not need any special initialization,
      you can use the <code>ConfigurationProvider</code> class directly. It is
      able of creating an instance of a specified class (which must be derived
      from <code>AbstractConfiguration</code>). Let's take a look at an example
      where we want to add support for a configuration class called
      <code>MyConfiguration</code>. The corresponding tag in the configuration
      definition file should have the name <code>myconfig</code>. The code for
      registering the new provider and loading the configuration definition file
      looks as follows:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
DefaultConfigurationBuilder builder = new DefaultConfigurationBuilder();
DefaultConfigurationBuilder.ConfigurationProvider provider = new
  DefaultConfigurationBuilder.ConfigurationProvider(MyConfiguration.class);
builder.addConfigurationProvider("myconfig", provider);

builder.setFileName("configuration.xml");
Configuration config = builder.getConfiguration();
]]></source>
    <p>
      If your configuration provider is registered this way, your configuration
      definition file can contain the <code>myconfig</code> tag just as any
      other tag for declaring a configuration source:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <additional>
    <xml fileName="settings.xml"/>
    <myconfig delimiterParsingDisabled="true"/>
  </additional>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      As is demonstrated in this example, it is possible to specify attributes
      for initializing properties of your configuration object. In this example
      we set the default <code>delimiterParsingDisabled</code> property
      inherited from <code>AbstractConfiguration</code>. Of course you can set
      custom properties of your configuration class, too.
    </p>
    <p>
      If your custom configuration class is a file-based configuration, you
      should use the <code>FileConfigurationProvider</code> class instead of
      <code>ConfigurationProvider</code>. <code>FileConfigurationProvider</code>
      is another inner class of <code>DefaultConfigurationBuilder</code> that
      knows how to deal with file-based configurations: it ensures that the
      correct base path is set and takes care of invoking the <code>load()</code>
      method.
    </p>
    <p>
      If your custom configuration class requires special initialization, you
      need to create your own provider class that extends
      <code>ConfigurationProvider</code>. Here you will have to override the
      <code>getConfiguration(ConfigurationDeclaration)</code> method, which is
      responsible for creating the configuration instance (all information
      necessary for this purpose can be obtained from the passed in declaration
      object). It is recommended that you call the inherited method first,
      which will instantiate and initialize the new configuration object. Then
      you can perform your specific initialization.
    </p>
    </subsection>
    </section>
</body>

</document>
