<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Migration Guide for 2.0</title>
 </properties>

<body>
    <section name="Migration Guide to Version 2.0">
    <p>
      Version 2.0 of <em>Commons Configuration</em> is the result of a major
      redesign of this library. Some concepts used within the 1.x version
      series have changed significantly or have even been replaced by alternative
      approaches. Therefore, you cannot simply drop the new jar in your classpath
      and expect that everything continues to work.
    </p>
    <p>
      This document aims at supporting with the migration from version 1.x of
      <em>Commons Configuration</em> to version 2.0. Target audience are
      users of an older version who want to upgrade. The document describes the
      problems which are likely to be encountered during this migration and
      discusses possible strategies or solutions.
    </p>
    <p>
      Also note that the <a href="user_guide.html">user's guide</a> has been
      fully reworked to cover all the new features and concepts offered by
      <em>Commons Configuration</em> 2.0. Because of that, this document will not
      describe interfaces or classes in detail, but simply refer to the
      corresponding sections of the user guide.
    </p>
    <p>
      This document has the following content:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#Structural_Changes">Structural Changes</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <subsection name="Structural Changes">
    <p>
      The most obvious change you will notice at the very beginning is that
      the root package was renamed to <code>org.apache.commons.configuration2</code>
      - the major version is now part of the package name. This certainly makes
      migration harder, but it is the only possibility to avoid jar hell.
      Imagine for a moment that we had kept the old package name. This
      would work well for applications that are the only user of the
      <em>Commons Configuration</em> library. But as soon as there are 3rd
      party libraries also using this component, but in version 1.x, then there
      is real trouble: The class path then contains classes with identical
      names in different versions - results will be unpredictable! The change
      of the package name solves this problem because the new version can now
      co-exist with an old version without interfering.
    </p>
    <p>
      For the same reason the <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a>
      coordinates have been changed. Use the following dependency declaration
      in your pom:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<dependency>
  <groupId>org.apache.commons</groupId>
  <artifactId>commons-configuration2</artifactId>
  <version>2.0</version>
</dependency>
]]></source>
    <p>
      So for Maven version 2.0 is a completely different artifact. This
      allows a peaceful co-existence of <em>Commons Configuration</em> 1.x and
      2.0 in the dependency set of a project.
    </p>
    </subsection>

  </section>
</body>

</document>