<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Combined Configurations</title>
  <author email="oheger@apache.com">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
    <section name="Combined Configuration">
    <p>
      The <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/CombinedConfiguration.html">
      CombinedConfiguration</a></code> class provides an alternative for handling
      multiple configuration sources. Its API is very similar to the
      <code>CompositeConfiguration</code> class, which was discussed in the
      <a href="howto_compositeconfiguration.html#Composite Configuration Details">last
      section</a>. There are the following differences however:
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>A <code>CombinedConfiguration</code> is a truely
        <a href="howto_xml.html#Hierarchical properties">hierarchical
        configuration</a>. This means that all the enhanced facilities
        provided by <code>HierarchicalConfiguration</code> (e.g. expression
        engines) can be used.</li>
        <li>A <code>CombinedConfiguration</code> is not limited to implementing
        an override semantics for the properties of the contained configurations.
        Instead it has the concept of so-called <em>node combiners</em>, which
        know how properties of multiple configuration sources can be combined.
        Node combiners are discussed later in detail. For instance, there is a
        node combiner implementation available that constructs a union of the
        contained configurations.</li>
        <li>Contained configurations can be assigned a name. They can later be
        accessed by their name.</li>
        <li>Each contained configuration can have an optional prefix. Its
        properties are then added under this prefix to the combined
        configuration.</li>
        <li>There is no concept of an <em>in memory configuration</em>. Changes
        to a combined configuration are handled in a different way.</li>
      </ul>
   	</p>

    <subsection name="How it works">
    <p>
      A <code>CombinedConfiguration</code> provides a logic view on the
      properties of the configurations it contains. This view is determined
      by the associated node combiner object. Because of that it must be
      re-constructed whenever one of these contained configurations is
      changed.
    </p>
    <p>
      To achieve this, a <code>CombinedConfiguration</code> object registers
      itself as an event listener at the configurations that are added to it.
      It will then be notified for every modification that occurs. If such a
      notification is received, the internally managed view is invalidated.
      When a property of the combined configuration is to be accessed, the view
      is checked whether it is valid. If this is the case, the property's value
      can be directly fetched. Otherwise the associated node combiner is asked
      to re-construct the view.
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Node combiners">
    <p>
      A <em>node combiner</em> is an object of a class that inherits from the
      abstract <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/tree/NodeCombiner.html">NodeCombiner</a></code>
      class. This class defines an abstract <code>combine()</code> method, which
      takes the root nodes of two hierarchical configurations and returns the
      root node of the combined node structure. It is up to a concrete
      implementation how this combined structure will look like. Commons
      Configuration ships with the two concrete implementations
      <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/tree/OverrideCombiner.html">OverrideCombiner</a></code>
      and <code><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/configuration2/tree/UnionCombiner.html">UnionCombiner</a></code>,
      which implement an override and a union semantics respective.
    </p>
    <p>
      Constructing a combination of multiple node hierarchies is not a trivial
      task. The available implementations descend the passed in node hierarchies
      in a recursive manner to decide, which nodes have to be copied into the
      resulting structure. Under certain circumstances two nodes of the source
      structures can be combined into a single result node, but unfortunately
      this process cannot be fully automated, but sometimes needs some hints
      from the developer. As an example consider the following XML configuration
      sources:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <database>
    <tables>
      <table>
        <name>users</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>user_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
      </table>
    </tables>
  </database>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>and</p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <database>
    <tables>
      <table>
        <name>documents</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>document_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
      </table>
    </tables>
  </database>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      These two configuration sources define database tables. Each source
      defines one table. When constructing a union for these sources the result
      should look as follows:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <database>
    <tables>
      <table>
        <name>users</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>user_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
      </table>
      <table>
        <name>documents</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>document_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
      </table>
    </tables>
  </database>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      As you can see, the resulting structure contains two <code>table</code>
      nodes while the nodes <code>database</code> and <code>tables</code> appear
      only once. For a human being this is quite logic because <code>database</code>
      and <code>tables</code> define the overall structure of the configuration
      data, and there can be multiple tables. A node combiner however does not
      know anything about structure nodes, list nodes, or whatever. From its point of
      view there is no detectable difference between the <code>tables</code>
      nodes and the <code>table</code> nodes in the source structures: both
      appear once in each source file and have no values. So without any
      assistance the result constructed by the <code>UnionCombiner</code> when
      applied on the two example sources would be a bit different:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<configuration>
  <database>
    <tables>
      <table>
        <name>users</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>user_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
        <name>documents</name>
        <fields>
          <field>
            <name>document_id</name>
          </field>
          ...
        </fields>
      </table>
    </tables>
  </database>
</configuration>
]]></source>
    <p>
      Note that the <code>table</code> node would be considered a structure
      node, too, and would not be duplicated. This is probably not what was
      desired. To deal with such situations it is possible to tell the node
      combiner that certain nodes are list nodes and thus should not be
      combined. So in this concrete example the <code>table</code> node should
      be declared as a list node, then we would get the expected result. We will
      see below how this is done. Note that this explicit declaration of a list
      node is necessary only in situations where there is ambiguity. If in one
      of our example configuration sources multiple tables had been defined, the
      node combiner would have concluded itself that <code>table</code> is a list
      node and would have acted correspondigly.
    </p>
    </subsection>

	<subsection name="Constructing a CombinedConfiguration">
	<p>
      To create a <code>CombinedConfiguration</code> object you specify the node
      combiner to use and then add an arbitrary number of configurations. We will
      show how to construct a union configuration from the two example sources
      introduced earlier:
    </p>
<source><![CDATA[
// Load the source configurations
XMLConfiguration conf1 = new XMLConfiguration("table1.xml");
XMLConfiguration conf2 = new XMLConfiguration("table2.xml");

// Create and initialize the node combiner
NodeCombiner combiner = new UnionCombiner();
combiner.addListNode("table");  // mark table as list node
            // this is needed only if there are ambiguities

// Construct the combined configuration
CombinedConfiguration cc = new CombinedConfiguration(combiner);
cc.addConfiguration(conf1, "tab1");
cc.addConfiguration(conf2);
]]></source>
    <p>
      Here we also specified a name for one of the configurations, so it can
      later be accessed by <code>cc.getConfiguration("tab1");</code>. Access by
      index is also supported. After that the properties in the combined
      configuration can be accessed as if it were a normal hierarchical
      configuration
    </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Dealing with changes">
    <p>
      There is nothing that prevents you from updating a combined configuration,
      e.g. by calling methods like <code>addProperty()</code> or
      <code>removeProperty()</code>. The problem is that depending on the used
      node combiner it might no be clear, which of the contained configurations
      will be modified or whether one is modified at all.
    </p>
    <p>
      Typical node combiners work by copying parts of the node structures of
      the source configurations into the target structure and linking them
      togehter using special link nodes. So updates of the combined node structure
      will either effect nodes from one of the contained configuration (then
      the changes are directly visible in this configuration) or one of the link
      nodes (then they cannot really be saved).
    </p>
    <p>
      It is also possible that a change is done at the combined node structure,
      which is not compatible with the current node combiner. Imagine that an
      <code>OverrideCombiner</code> is used and that a
      property should be removed. This property will then be removed from one
      of the contained configurations. Now it may happen that this removed
      property had hidden property values of other contained configurations.
      Their values won't become visible automatically, but only after the
      combined view was re-constructed.
    </p>
    <p>
      Because of that it is recommended that changes are not done at the
      combined configuration, but only at contained configurations. This way
      the correct configuration to be updated can unambigously be identified.
      Obtaining the configuration to be updated from the combined configuration
      is easy when it was given a name.
    </p>
    </subsection>
	</section>
</body>

</document>