<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Apache Commons Configuration Security Reports</title>
        <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Team</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="General Information">
            <p>
                For information about reporting or asking questions about
                security problems, please see the
                <a href="https://commons.apache.org/security.html">security page</a>
                of the Apache Commons project.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Apache Commons Configuration Security Vulnerabilities">
            <p>This page lists all security vulnerabilities fixed in
                released versions of Apache Commons Configuration.
            </p>

            <p>Please note that binary patches are never provided. If you
                need to apply a source code patch, use the building
                instructions for the Commons Configuration version that you are
                using.
            </p>

            <p>
                If you need help on building Commons Configuration or other help
                on following the instructions to mitigate the known
                vulnerabilities listed here, please send your questions to the
                public
                <a href="mail-lists.html">Compress Users mailing
                    list
                </a>
                .
            </p>

            <p>If you have encountered an unlisted security vulnerability
                or other unexpected behavior that has security impact, or if
                the descriptions here are incomplete, please report them
                privately to the Apache Security Team. Thank you.
            </p>

            <subsection name="Fixed in Apache Commons Configuration 2.8.0">
                <ul>
                    <p>
                        <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2022-33980">CVE-2022-33980</a>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Apache Commons Configuration performs variable interpolation, allowing properties to be dynamically evaluated and
                        expanded. The standard format for interpolation is "${prefix:name}", where "prefix" is used to
                        locate an instance of org.apache.commons.configuration2.interpol.Lookup that performs the
                        interpolation. Starting with version 2.4 and continuing through 2.7, the set of default Lookup
                        instances included interpolators that could result in arbitrary code execution or contact with
                        remote servers. These lookups are: - "script" - execute expressions using the JVM script
                        execution engine (javax.script) - "dns" - resolve dns records - "url" - load values from urls,
                        including from remote servers Applications using the interpolation defaults in the affected
                        versions may be vulnerable to remote code execution or unintentional contact with remote servers
                        if untrusted configuration values are used. Users are recommended to upgrade to Apache Commons
                        Configuration 2.8.0, which disables the problematic interpolators by default.
                    </p>
                </ul>

            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="Errors and Omissions">
            <p>
                Please report any errors or omissions to
                <a href="mail-lists.html">the dev mailing list</a>
                .
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
