<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Building</title>
        <author email="oheger@apache.org">Oliver Heger</author>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Overview">
          <p>
            Commons Configuration can be built using
            <a href="http://maven.apache.org">maven</a> or
            <a href="http://ant.apache.org">ant</a>. While building on a JDK
            1.4 and higher should be no problem for JDK 1.3 (which is the
            minimum required JDK) some preparations are necessary. This is
            covered in full detail in the Building with JDK 1.3 section below.
          </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Maven 2">
          <p>
            Commons Configuration uses Maven 2 as its build tool. To build the Configuration
            jar, change into the directory where the source distribution resides and run
            "mvn install". This will compile the source and tests, run the tests, and then
            package the jar. The jar will also be copied into the local maven repository
            for use by other builds.
          </p>
          <p>
            To build the web site run "mvn site". When it completes the web site will reside in
            the target/site directory and may be viewed by opening target/site/index.html.
          </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Running Functional Tests">
          <p>
            <code>TestWebdavConfigurationBuilder</code> is a functional test that tests
            DefaultConfigurationBuilder with the configuration files stored in a WebDAV
            server. To run the test the steps that follow
            <ol>
              <li>Copy all the files in the conf directory to the WebDAV server. Not all the
              files are required but it is generally easier to use a tool like cadaver
              and do an mput than try to copy the required files individually.</li>
              <li>Add the following to the profiles section of settings.xml in the Maven home
              directory. Modify the urls to match your setup.
<source><![CDATA[
   <profile>
    <profile>
      <id>webdav</id>
      <activation>
        <activeByDefault>false</activeByDefault>
      </activation>
      <properties>
        <test.webdav.base>webdav://vfsusr:vfstest@192.168.10.133:80/conf</test.webdav.base>
      </properties>
    </profile>]]></source></li>
              <li>run "mvn -P webdav test -Dtest=TestWebdavConfigurationBuilder". The test
              can also be run using "mvn -P webdav test" but this will run all the unit tests
              in addition to the WebDAV test.</li>
            </ol>
          </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Maven 1 Goals">
          <p>
            To build the Configuration jar file using Maven 1, change into the directory where you
            unzipped the source distribution or where you checked out the sources from SVN and run
            "maven jar". The result will be in the (newly created) "target"
            subdirectory.
          </p>
          <p>
            To build the Javadocs, run "maven javadoc".
            The result will be in "target/docs/apidocs".
          </p>
          <p>
            To build the full website, run "maven site".
            The result will be in "target/docs".
          </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Ant Goals">
          <p>
            To build a jar file, change into Configuration's root directory and run "ant jar".
            The result will be in the "target" subdirectory.
          </p>
          <p>
            To build the Javadocs, run "ant javadoc".
            The result will be in "target/docs/apidocs".
          </p>
        </section>
        
        <section name="Building with JDK 1.3">
          <p>
            If you want to build Commons Configuration on a JDK 1.3, you will
            face two problems:
          </p>
          <p>
            The first problem is that JDK 1.3 does not contain the JDBC 2.0
            standard extensions, which are used by the
            <code>DatabaseConfiguration</code> class. Unfortunately, due to legal
            issues, the jar file containing these extensions cannot be
            distributed through the typical maven repositories and automatically
            downloaded. To resolve this issue perform the following steps:
          </p>
          <p>
            <ul>
              <li>Download the JDBC 2.0 Optional Package from
              <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/download.html">
              http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/download.html</a> and store
              the jdbc-stdext-2.0.jar somewhere on your hard disk.</li>
              <li>Create a <code>build.properties</code> file in the Configuration
              root directory that must contain the following line:<br/>
              <code>dependency.jdbc = <em>&lt;path to jdbc-stdext-2.0.jar&gt;</em></code></li>
            </ul>
          </p>
          <p>
            The second problem is related to a test class for
            <code>DatabaseConfiguration</code> that makes use of
            <a href="http://hsqldb.org">hsqldb</a>. At the time of writing this, the
            hsqldb jar files distributed on the ibiblio maven repository only
            support JDK 1.4 and higher. This makes the tests fail with a class
            not found exception for <code>java.sql.SavePoint</code>. There are
            some workarounds for this problem:
          </p>
          <p>
            <ul>
              <li>Disable the failing test class
              (<code>org.apache.commons.configuration.TestDatabaseConfiguration</code>)
              in the build script. For instance if building with maven, this can
              be done with an <code>excludes</code> element in the
              <code>unitTest</code> section of <code>project.xml</code>.</li>
              <li>It is possible to download a hsqldb distribution and recompile
              on JDK 1.3. The jar that is created this way will cause no
              problems on a JDK 1.3.</li>
              <li>Another solution would be to run maven on a JDK 1.4 or higher and use
              the <code>maven.compile.executable</code> property to point to
              a JDK 1.3 compiler. This will ensure that the classes are compiled
              on JDK 1.3, but the tests are run on the JDK maven is executing.
              Refer to the documentation of the
              <a href="http://maven.apache.org/maven-1.x/reference/plugins/java/">
              Maven Java Plug-in</a> for further information.</li>
            </ul>
          </p>
          <p>
            If these problems are solved, the build can be performed as
            described above.
          </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Setting custom build parameters">
          <p>
            Both the maven 1 and the ant build script support a file called
            <code>build.properties</code> that can contain custom properties
            definitions. If this file exists in the project's root directory,
            it will be read and the properties it defines will be added to the
            running build script. This mechanism allows for customizing the
            build process without the need of changing the main build scripts.
          </p>
          <p>
            One use case for setting custom build properties would be to build
            for a specific JDK version: If you build the jar on a JDK 1.5 for
            instance, the classes won't be compatible with older JDK versions.
            To enforce compatibility you can create a <code>build.properties</code>
            file containing the following maven specific settings:
          </p>
          <source><![CDATA[
maven.compile.source = 1.3
maven.compile.target = 1.3
]]></source>
        </section>
    </body>

</document>
